<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saint Paules agonie A sermon preached at Leicester, at the ordinary monthly lecture: specially touching the motions of sinne, remaining in the regenerate. By A. Cade, Bacheler in Diuinity, and of Bilsdon in Leycester-shire.</title>
            <author>Cade, Anthony, 1564?-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843072</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1059:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saint Paules agonie A sermon preached at Leicester, at the ordinary monthly lecture: specially touching the motions of sinne, remaining in the regenerate. By A. Cade, Bacheler in Diuinity, and of Bilsdon in Leycester-shire.</title>
                  <author>Cade, Anthony, 1564?-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Bernard Alsop, and are to be sold at his house by Saint Annes Church neere Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7780:1"/>
            <p>SAINT PAVLES AGONIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A SERMON PREACHED</hi> at LEICESTER, at the <hi>Ordinary Monthly Lecture:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Specially touching the Motions of Sinne, remaining <hi>in the Regenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY A. CADE, BACHELER in Diuinity, and of Bilſdon in <hi>Leyceſter-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GAL. 5.17.</hi>
               </bibl> The Fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirite, and the Spirite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fleſh, and theſe are contrary the one to the other: ſo that yee cannot doe the things that ye would.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by <hi>Bernard Alſop,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his houſe by Saint <hi>Annes</hi> Church neere Alderſgate. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7780:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7780:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE <hi>Lord Marqueſſe of Buckingham.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our goodneſſe continually prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in your greatneſſe, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of many, bindes all highly to honour you, and account you as a Conduit ordayned of God to conueigh many benefites from his <hi>Royall Maieſty</hi> vpon inferiours. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which, your Honourable kindneſſe to me, in prouiding for me, without my ſute or knowledge, a right famous and noble place, to rayſe my fortunes, and exerciſe my Miniſtery in, (the like whereof many haue ſought with great ſute, coſt, and labor, and haue not found) deſerueth all thankefulneſſe that can bee imagined, much more then can bee performed. But feeling my ſelfe too weake for the greatneſſe of that place (not for my doctrine, the ſoundneſſe &amp; whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe whereof I am ready to teſtifie and iuſtifie, if need require, with my bloud) but by the weakneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:7780:3"/> of my voyce, not able to reach the halfe of that ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Church and numerous people. I humbly pray your Honour to take without offence my Refuſall, and my harty deſire that that great and worthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may be furniſhed with a man of a ſtronger voyce and better ſides, who may doe there much more good then my ſelfe: who in my declining yeares muſt rather affect a more retired life, and a charge more poſſible to be performed with better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction to my ſelfe and to Gods people. I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore honour your goodneſſe and your Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for this fauour, which I publikely proteſt by the Dedication of this Sermon, in Stile ſimple, but in matter ſound and ſubſtantiall: which hauing lately preached, I thought good to publiſh, at the requeſt of many my good friends of religious hearts: the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to oppoſe the ſpreading of thoſe opinionate &amp; fanſifull younglings, who drawing bad iuyce from <hi>Arminius</hi> and <hi>Vorſtius,</hi> beginne to bud and bloſſome in our Academie, whence nothing but good and wholeſome food ſhould be brought into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. To ſhew how firmely our doctrine in theſe points is founded vpon the Scriptures, and conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the Fathers of the Primitiue, and all ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, and what exceeding good vſe and profite it yeeldeth, and how farre theſe men ſwerue from it, and from al true experience of Gods Saints in the ſtate of Grace and Regeneration: I haue penned &amp; publiſhed this Sermon, and wiſh all good men to put to their hands to repreſſe all ſuch hurtfull grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innouations, diſquieting, diſtracting, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing
<pb facs="tcp:7780:3"/> the peace and beauty of our Church, to the offence and hazarding of many Soules. And ſo I ceaſe to trouble your Honour, but ſhall neuer ceaſe praying for you, and honouring you as fitteth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humble and thankefull Chaplen,</hi> Anthony Cade.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7780:4"/>
            <head>An admonition to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, the Concourſe of many learned Miniſters at our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Monthly Lecture (lately before intermitted) whereunto now alſo reſorted (by occaſion) many learned Iuditious Gentlemen; required mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of more then ordinary worth and learning. To ſatiſfie whom, If I haue layd the grounds of my Sermon more Schoole-like then thou thinkeſt fitte for the Country, beare with mee, now thou knoweſt the occaſion.</p>
            <p>Know alſo, that I haue more enlarged thoſe pointes to ground men more ſtrongly againſt Innouators: for that I hope this little Booke may come, and be read, where grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will not. The other points thence deducted are plaine enough for the ſimpleſt Hearers, and applyed to theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, <hi>Apollo</hi> water. The Lord giue a bleſſed encreaſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. C</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7780:4"/>
            <head>SAINT PAVLES <hi>AGONIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. VII.XXIIII.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe wordes are the ſhutting vp of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous Combat (which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribeth from the 13. Verſe) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>Spirite:</hi> that is, betwixt our naturall corruption luſting one way, and Gods holy Spirite mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs another way. For as in this life our <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> is enlightned, but in part (now wee ſee but as through a Glaſſe darkely<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12</note>): So our <hi>Wils</hi> and <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> are reformed but in part, very weakely to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that little which wee ſee (Wee cannot doe the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7780:5"/> things that wee would<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note>). Our corruptions though abated, yet are not extinguiſhed by Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but our <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Will</hi> continue ſtill partly <hi>fleſh,</hi> and partly <hi>ſpirite,</hi> that is, partly <hi>grace,</hi> and partly <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> A reformation begunne, but not finiſhed, like the Ayre in the dawning of the day,<note place="margin">Sanctificatio inchoata, non conſummata.</note> neyther wholy yet enlightned, nor wholly remayning darke<note n="c" place="margin">Yet ſhineth more and more vntill the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect day. Pro. 4.1 8,</note> or water blood-warme, neyther perfectly hore, nor perfectly cold: but the light and darkeneſſe of the <hi>minde,</hi> the heate and cold of the <hi>Will,</hi> ſo mixed and intermedled together throughout, that there is a continuall ſtriſe betwixt them, which ſhall ouercome the other, and ouerrunne the Soule. This Combat the Apoſtle deſcribeth moſt mouingly and feelingly in his owne perſon, finding his own ſoule (as it were) diſtracted into two contrary factions, and ſubiect to two contrary Rulers, and guided by two contrary lawes (as a ſhippe toſſed by two contrary winds or tides.) The inner man, (or part Regenerate) euer eying the law of God, &amp; ſtriuing for perfection; but hindred by another Law in his Members (the part vnregenerate) rebelling againſt the Law of his mind, and ſtriuing both againſt his will (Verſ. 15,) and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his knowledge (Verſe 16.) to carry him away to ſinne (Verſ, 17) ſo hindring the good which hee would doe, (verſe 18.) and drawing him to the euill which he would not doe (ver. 19.) which again he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peateth in the verſes following, as a thing neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough obſerued, at the laſt, as one amazed, and much aſtoniſhed to find in himſelfe ſo much imperfection, hee breaketh out into this paſſionate exclamation, <hi>O
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7780:5"/> wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from the body of this death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words I obſerue fiue things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Matter that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here complaines of, <hi>Sinne,</hi> which he cals <hi>the body of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The Subiect or party that he finds it in. In him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Wretched man that I am: Who ſhall deliuer me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 That he is exceeding ſenſible of it, feeles the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and ſtirring of it, as appeares by the diſcourſe: and here it driues him into a paſſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is the onely thing that grieues him. Hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts himſelfe wretched by it, <hi>O wretched man that I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 The ſight and feeling of his ſin makes him ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſeeke for a remedy, <hi>Who ſhall deliuer me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or to aſcend from the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> to the <hi>Theſis,</hi> from Saint <hi>Paules</hi> particular to the generall of all Gods children, we ſhall finde.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The irregular motions of luſt in Man, to bee ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This ſinne, or thoſe motions to remayne in the Regenerate.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The Regenerate aboue other men to bee excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſenſible of them.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the ſight and feeling of them is the thing that ſpecially grieues them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 And laſtly, that this makes them earneſtly ſeeke for comfort and deliuerance.</p>
            <p>Theſe are great points, worthy our handling, worthy your attention.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:7780:6"/>1 For the firſt: In the whole Diſcourſe of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, note two things: Firſt, that it is a thing <hi>Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary,</hi> verſ. 15. I allow not that which I doe; for what I would doe, that do I not, but what I hate that doe I, and verſe 16. If then I do that which I would not, I conſent to the law, that it is good, and ver. 18. to will is preſent with mee, and 22. I delight in the law concerning the inner man.</p>
            <p>Note ſecondly, that ſtill hee calles it Euill and Sinne, and here The body of <hi>Death,</hi> by a <hi>Metonomya Effecti,</hi> the very matter and cauſe of death, which Chap. 6.6. He calleth <hi>The body of Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ioyne theſe two together, that it is <hi>Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary,</hi> and that it is <hi>Sinne,</hi> and you rayſe this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>I</label> 
               <hi>The irregular motions of Luſt, though not yeeded vnto, are Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>I</label> I meane all kind of luſts, not onely libidinous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but thoſe alſo of Malice, Pride, Couetouſnes, Gluttony, Eaſe, Diſobedience, and ſuch like. They are all ſinne. The Reaſon is. I. Becauſe they diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree from the law of God, (which is <hi>Regula iuſticitiae</hi>) for what is ſinne, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.4.) an Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, diſcrepance, and vnconformity to Gods Law.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6, 5. Mat. 22.37.</note>2 Againe, God reequires Loue with all the hart, minde, ſoule and ſtrength, that is, with all the parts, and faculties of body and ſoule, and all the power of them: therefore, as to loue any thing beſides him, not for him, is ſinne: ſo not to loue him withall thy power, is a ſinne: the one turning aſide from thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7780:6"/> the other comming ſhort of thy duety: both faulty, both ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3 Againe, this is not Innocency and cleannes from euill, though without conſent.<note place="margin">See S. Auguſt. lib. 3. de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cap. 6. &amp; 7. Auguſtine was the firſt that wrote of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne, teſte Bellarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. lib. 1. de pec. orig. cap. 1.</note> It is ſtill cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, vncleanneſſe, imperfection, and is indeede the ſtirring and mouing of that corruption of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which in <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> time began to be called <hi>Originall Sinne,</hi> which is not onely <hi>Languor Naturae,</hi> (as many haue called it) nor onely <hi>Carentia iuſtitiae debitae ineſſe</hi> (according to that famous definition of <hi>Anſelm</hi>) a want of that righteouſneſſe which ought to be in man; nor onely <hi>Difformitas</hi> (as Doctor <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton</hi> cals it) an vnconformity, or diuers form, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the Image of God, firſt imprinted vpon Man, (which yet is inough to make it ſinne) but <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitas</hi> (which is more) a deformity, miſhappe, and corrupt forme. For we ſhall finde here in S. <hi>Paules</hi> diſcourſe of it, not onely a <hi>Priuation of Originall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> or a <hi>Languor Naturae,</hi> vnapt to doe good: but further, a <hi>Poſition of ſinnefull corruption,</hi> a ſtirring and rebelling of Luſt, prouoking to Euill. For that <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guor</hi> it had beene enough to ſay, <hi>I know that in mee, that is in my fleſh dwelleth no good thing,</hi> verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. but hee proceedeth, and addeth, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. <hi>I ſee another law in my members, warring againſt the Law of my minde, and bringing me into captiuity vnto the Law of Sinne, which is in my members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vnderſtand we then, that wee are all <hi>ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſinne hath our mother conceyued vs.</hi> Pſal. 51.5, For <hi>Adam</hi> ſinning in perſon, hath corrupted our whole nature, ſo that together with our ſubſtance is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7780:7"/> mixed a matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of corruption, which in the framing and growing of our members, groweth, and is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the naturall heate of our mothers: a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in the body which in time will bring diſeaſes and naturall death: and a corruption cleauing to the ſoule, which in time will bring foorth actuall ſinnes, and eternall death: ſo that being conceyued and borne man, wee are conceyued and borne ſinnefull men,<note place="margin">Bern. meditat. cap, 2. initio.</note> according to that of <hi>S. Bernard, Parentes ante fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunt damnatum quam natum:</hi> ſo are we all by Nature the children of wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. This corruption is called <hi>The old man</hi> Rom. 6.6. and heere <hi>The Body of Death,</hi> which wee muſt labour to mortifie, crucifie, and deſtroy: for this without yeelding vnto, is <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne,</hi> but with yeelding and delight groweth into <hi>Actuall ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in cap. 5 Mathaei. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron. in cap. 1. Amos. Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe quae mala ſunt: ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cogitationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus adquicuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe peruerſis: tertius, quod mente decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueris, op re co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: quartu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, poſt peccatum non agere poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam.</note> 
               <hi>Saint Hierom</hi> diſtinguiſheth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Pathos</hi> and <hi>Propatheia,</hi> paſſion and fore-paſſion. <hi>Pathos</hi> is paſſion with conſent. <hi>Propatheia</hi> is a tickling of luſt without conſent, both are ſinnes though in ſeuerall degrees. The ſame Father thus diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth ſinne. The firſt ſinne is to thinke euill things: the ſecond, to reſt vpon, or yeeld to the euil thoughts: the third to performe in deede what thou haſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in minde: the fourth, not to repent after thy ſinne.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſpeakes of theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as <hi>Inuoluntary,</hi> without yeelding to them, and againſt his mind, as <hi>Saint Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nobis reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantibus multa in nobis operatur peccatum,</hi> Sinne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many things in vs while wee ſtriue againſt it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he cals it in plaine termes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sinne, yea
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7780:7"/> it is obſerued by <hi>Chemnicius</hi> (a worthy iudicious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine) that in the 6. Chapter he calls it fiue times ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Chemnic'j examen part. 1. de relliq. pec. orig. pag. 224. Editionis 1590. in 8. Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. 5. cap. 3 Tolet in ep: ad Rom. cap. 7 &amp; 8.</p>
                  <p>Bellarm. de amiſſ. grat. &amp; ſtat. pecc. lib. 5. cap. 10.</p>
               </note> in this 7. Chapter 6. times, in the 8. thrice. And Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> grounding on this place, calles it plainely Sinne, <hi>Coucupiſcentia carnis, aduerſus quam bonus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcit Spiritus. &amp; peccatum eſt, &amp; poena peccati, &amp; cauſa peccati.</hi> The luſt of the fleſh, againſt which the good Spirit luſteth, is both ſinne, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne, and the cauſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>Well may I then wonder at the Ieſuites, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Tolet, Bellarmine</hi> and others, that will needes confute both Saint <hi>Paules</hi> Greeke, and Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> Latine, and ſay they ſpeake both vnproperly, calling that <hi>Peccatum,</hi> which is but <hi>fomes peccati,</hi> the matter and tinder of ſinne, where <hi>Tolet</hi> yet confeſſeth plainely two thinges: Firſt, that it is not onely Saint <hi>Auſtens</hi> word, but his perpetuall doctrine: and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that the Papiſts now wholly depart from it. <hi>Doctrina eſt frequentiſſima in Auguſtino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tolet. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>à qua tamen pro nunc recedimus.</hi> Theſe are they that ſo magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Fathers in ſhew, but reiect them in deed, both for <hi>Interpretations</hi> and <hi>Dogmata,</hi> for the ſence of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and points of Doctrine. Theſe Children will teach their Fathers to ſpeake: Theſe Schoolemen will ſet Chriſt and his Apoſtles to Schoole: ſurely, theſe new Ieſuites,<note place="margin">Decet vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt ſermones noſtros &amp; ſcripturis, &amp; Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum verbis, attemperemus ſaith Vega leſ.</note> both in ſpeaking and doing are farre vnlike the olde Chriſtians. But let vs learne to ſpeake of that great Father Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and of his great Father Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> rather then of <hi>Tolet</hi> or <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or any other Cardinall or Ieſuit.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Yet further Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calles it not onely Sin,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7780:8"/> but <hi>Deadly ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Stipendiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati mors. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 6. verſ. vlt.</note> the <hi>Body of Death,</hi> as hee ſpeakes elſewhere generally of all ſinne without diſtinction: <hi>The wages of ſinne is death.</hi> All ſinnes with him are mortall, he knew not theſe <hi>veniall, triuiall, peccadilia,</hi> little trifling ſinnes, not worthy to be called ſinnes, which Papiſts ſo mince, and make nothing of: but euen for theſe, the leaſt of all other, he cryeth out, as at deadly wounds of his ſoule, <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of Death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diſtinction which the Romaniſts now teach, neyther <hi>Paul</hi> knew, nor the<note n="z" place="margin">See D. Field of the Church. Booke 3. chap. 7. &amp; D. Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> Church many ages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: neyther are themſelues yet agreede vpon it.<note n="a" place="margin">As they are cited by Azor. Inſtit. moral. part 1. lib. 4. cap. 8. § dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> 
               <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga</hi> the Ieſuite, and with him <hi>Durandus</hi> and <hi>Catetanus,</hi> thinke all ſinne to be againſt the Law:<note n="b" place="margin">Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. de amiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one gratiae. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 1. cap. 11. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vlt. &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim in eo libro vbi Azorius haec habet: Non ſunt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata venial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> proprie contra lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> peccat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> beates them down, and teacheth that mortall ſinne is againſt the Law, and Veniall ſinne only beſides the law.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Azorius ibid.</note>
               <hi>Azorius</hi> beateth him downe, and ſayth, <hi>Veniall</hi> is alſo againſt the Law. And<note n="d" place="margin">Greg. de Val. De differentia veteris &amp; novae legis, part. 2, c. 2. § Deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ne intelligi quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſt quod non ſit legis alicuius tranſgreſsio.</note> 
               <hi>Valentianus</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that no man can conceiue of ſinne but as a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion of the Law. Here is Ieſuite againſt Ieſuite, like <hi>Cadmus</hi> his ſerpentine teeth, euer as they ſpring vp, one brother beates downe another.<note n="e" place="margin">Ovid. Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morph: lib: 3. fab. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, All ſinne legally conſidered is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, but Evangelically is veniall, except the ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt. By his owne merit, <hi>mortall,</hi> by Chriſts mercy, <hi>veniall: Mortall</hi> is the naturall fleſhly, vnregenerate man (for hee that beleeueth not is condemned already, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.18. For<note n="f" place="margin">Magiſt. ſent lib. 2 diſt. 25. g. non poteſt non peccare etiam damnabiliter.</note> 
               <hi>hee can not but ſinne damnably</hi>) But <hi>Veniall</hi> to the <hi>Regenerate,</hi> though ſtill ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, <hi>There is no condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7780:8"/> to thoſe that are in Chriſt Ieſus. Quibus</hi> (ſaith Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten) <hi>remiſſus eſt reatus culpae &amp; peccati, quamuis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat actus</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Aug: Contra duas ep. Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giani, lib: 1. cap: 13. D. Morton, Appeal: lib: 5. ca: 22. ſectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 4. D. White Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſ. 38. D. Morton appeal: lib: 5, cap: 11, ſect: 5</note>. The diſtinction is not in the ſinne, but in the couenants, and in the perſons: for in the <hi>Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate,</hi> and by the <hi>Couenant</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> it diſſolueth not the league and loue betwixt God and Man, and ſo is <hi>Veniall:</hi> in others alſo is <hi>mortall,</hi> and ſo is all ſinne in all men, by his owne nature. In which regard <hi>S. Paul</hi> cals the leaſt ſinne here, <hi>the body of Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet wee make not all ſins equall, as the Stoiks among the Philoſophers, and the Iouinians among the Heretikes. Happily they may be<note n="h" place="margin">aeque pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata.</note> 
               <hi>equally ſinnes</hi> by their forme, as breaches of the law, and deſeruing wrath: though not<note n="i" place="margin">aequalia peccata.</note> 
               <hi>equall ſinnes</hi> in their matter, as if all were hainous alike. To be angry with thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without cauſe, is a ſin (formally): to reuile him,<note place="margin">Matth: 5, 22,</note> a worſe ſin: to kill him, worſt of all: but the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth iudgement, that is death (ſayth<note n="k" place="margin">Maldonatus Ieſuita. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Matt: 5, 21, 22,</note> 
               <hi>Maldonate</hi>) So among the Iewes were foure capitall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſtrangling, heading, ſtoning, and burning:<note place="margin">Maldonat: ibid: in verſ: 22, in fine,</note> all deathes, yet different in grieuouſneſſe and ſhame: arguing the ſinnes ſo puniſhed, to be all deadly, and yet vnequall in the hainouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>The Concluſion is, euen for theſe ſinnes, the leaſt of al other. The irregular motions of corrupt nature, euen without conſent, Saint <hi>Paule</hi> cryes out as at deadly ſinnes: <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of Death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe, </seg>1</label> The conſideration of this may firſt humble vs great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. If it humbled <hi>Abraham</hi> much to remember that hee was but duſt and aſhes<note n="l" place="margin">Gen: 18, 27,</note>: much more ſhould it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7780:9"/> humble vs to know that wee are much worſe, lumps of ſinne and corruption. A grieuous thing for good <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iob. 2.7.8</note> to be all ouerrunne with filthy ouzing ſores and vlcers, to ſit ſcraping them with a potſhard vpon the aſhes,<note place="margin">Greg. Morals vpon Iob.</note> 
               <hi>ſterquilinium ſuper ſterquilinio,</hi> ſitting like one dunghill vpon another, no better then a liuing and a walking dunghill: but we are much worſe in reſpect of ſin in our whole nature, all corrupt, leprous, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, like a cloth defiled with menſtrous bloud, which corruption if it breake not out into monſtrous ſins, (as it doth in many) yet the being of it in vs ſhould much abaſh vs, and cauſe vs to walke before the Lord in feare and trembling. As wee carry in our bodyes the ſeedes of mortality, and the matter of all diſeaſes, tending to diſſolution, or the firſt death: ſo in our ſoules and whole nature, the ſeedes and matter of deſtruction, or the ſecond death, and as our diſeaſes grieue and humble vs, ſo much more ſhould our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full corruption: as the firſt death terrifies, ſo much more ſhould the ſecond affright vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe, </seg>2</label> This ſhould alſo make vs carefull and heedful, to watch ouer and keepe down our inbred corruptions, that they breake not out into <hi>actuall ſinne,</hi> by getting conſent, gaining delight, and ſo comming to raigne in vs: As when wee feele the pricking of an olde diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, we are wary of our dyet, of cold, heat, ſurfetting, intemperancy, or any thing that may increaſe it.</p>
            <p>A hard matter it is to deny our ſelues, to mortifie our flattring luſts, to be at continuall warre with our owne pleaſing nature: but ſo we muſt be, if wee will be Chriſtians. And the more familiar and pleaſing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7780:9"/> this enemy is, that was borne and bred and brought vp with vs, and the fayrer her pretences, tickling our eares to fauour our ſelues, to pleaſe our deſires,<note place="margin">The great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntreſſe of. the world,</note> to ſatiſfie our owne luſts: the more it is to be ſuſpected, the more dangerous to be accounted, and the more carefull and heedfull we muſt bee, to keepe it vnder, that it get no power ouer vs. But of this more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. The ſecond point is,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doc. </seg>2</label> II <hi>This ſinne remayneth in the Regenerate.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>For here Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes in his owne perſon.<note place="margin">Valent: de Miſſa, contra Herbrandum. Tolet: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Rom: 7, 22, As if Paul ſpake in his owne perſon, by a figure onely.</note> 
               <hi>O wretched man, that I AM, who ſhall deliuer ME?</hi> But <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> a famous Ieſuite, and Cardinall <hi>Tolet,</hi> and many other of their fellowes (though not all) vnderſtand all this <hi>Combat</hi> to be deſcribed in the perſon of a man vnregenerate, ſtill vnder the Law, not vnder Grace, and to be betwixt <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite</hi> or <hi>Senſuality,</hi> like that of the Poet,
<q>Video meliora, proboque, Deteriora ſequor.</q> Indeed Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (in his younger yeares) took it, and taught it ſo:<note place="margin">Tolet: ibid: annot: 22,</note> but when his diligence was more awaked to ſearch, and his iudgement ripened to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, by his often conflicts with the Heretikes of his time, hee retracted that opinion and interpretation, and afterward expounded the whole diſcourſe of this Combat, as ſpoken properly in the perſon of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug: contra duas Epiſtolas Pelagiani, lib: 1, cap: 10, Vim mihi fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iunt illa ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, Condelec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor legi Dei ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aug. li. 6. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Pelagianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cap: 11. Ego cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aliter intellex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram, vel poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us non intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea melioribus &amp; intelligenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oribus ceſsi, vel potius ipſi (quod fatendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt) veritati, vt viderem in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Apoſtoli vocibus gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcentias di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micantiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sic Intellexit Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Ambroſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; caeteri eccleſiae San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctj, noti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores, &amp;c. Aug. lib. 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. cap. 1. &amp; lib. de praedeſt. ſanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cap. 4. &amp; lib. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra ep: Pelag: cap. 10. &amp; cap: 11: &amp; lib. 6. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Iulianum Pelag: cap, 11 Tolet: in Ro: 7. annot: 10. Tolet: tractat: ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do in loca quaedam epiſt: ad Rom: cap: 7 Vora (inquit) etiam eſt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina, qua ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo iuſtus in hoc ſeculo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> valet bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na carnis, &amp; vellet bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one operari, at non valet in hoc mortali cotpore donec per gratiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectionis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beretur, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino Radix pec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cati evellatur. Aug: lib: 1. cont: 2. epiſt: Pelag: cap: 13.</note> a man excellently regenerate, yet natural corruption remayning in him (not wholly aboliſhed) mouing and drawing him one way, and the ſpirite of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way. To which ſence Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was induced by two Arguments: one from the ſubſtance of the Text, rhe other from the conſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7780:10"/> before him. In the Text, theſe words (ſayeth hee) enforced me, <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. <hi>I delight in the Law of God according to tho inner man,</hi> which cannot agree to any but the Regenerate: as alſo thoſe words the laſt ver. <hi>Then I my ſelfe in my mind ſerue the Law of God:</hi> and thoſe, <hi>To will is preſent with me:</hi> for the vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate hath no ſuch will.</p>
            <p>And for the conſent of former Fathers he ſayth: Heretofore I vnderſtood this (combat) otherwiſe, or rather I vnderſtood it not: but afterwards I yeelded to better, and more intelligent Diuines, or rather (as I muſt confeſſe) to the truth it ſelfe, that I might ſee in theſe words of the Apoſtle, The Groues of Gods Saints, ſtriuing againſt fleſhly luſts. Thus haue <hi>Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Gregory, Ambroſe</hi> vnderſtood the place, and other holy and famous Doctors of the Church, &amp;c. And this was afterward Saint <hi>Auſtens</hi> perpetual and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant interpretation of this text, as may appeare by fiue ſeuerall places ìn his later workes, where he had occaſion to ſpeake of it.</p>
            <p>But though theſe Ieſuites reiect Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and all the vniforme conſent of <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> by him alleadged, and take vp ſtrangely an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by him retracted (ſuch is often their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Fathers) yet they graunt the point I ſpeake of, that <hi>Concupiſcence ſtill remayneth in the Regenerate,</hi> (though they are loath to call it ſinne, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth here) and that the Regenerate muſt labour to repreſſe it by the Spirit, as much as may be.</p>
            <p>This doctrine is true alſo ſaith <hi>Tolet,</hi> that a iuſt man cannot in this world doe good without the fight of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7780:10"/> his fleſh: and hee would doe good without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but in this mortall body he cannot, vntill by the grace of the Reſurrection he bee freed, and the root of ſin wholly plucked out.</p>
            <p>For this was the perpetual doctrine of the ancient Church. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> interpreting the firſt wordes of Rom. 8. teacheth that luſts rebelling againſt the law of the mind, are <hi>Originall ſin,</hi> which in the vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate is damnable, but in the regenerate<note n="a" place="margin">Ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae non habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quia remiſſus eſt reatus cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae &amp; peccata quamvis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat actus.</note> are not ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>counted ſins, becauſe the guilt of the fault and ſinne is forgiuin, though the act remayne.</p>
            <p>And S. <hi>Gregory</hi> interpreting this place of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> of the regenerate man ſayth, The moſt perfect men grieue at the ſimple motions of the fleſh ſuſtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wils: and that ſinne inhabiting in them, moues them againſt themſelues.</p>
            <p>And if any other Fathers count it not ſin, theyr meaning is that which S. <hi>Auſten</hi> expreſſeth <hi>(Remiſſus eſt reatus culpae, quamuis maneat actus)</hi> It is not imputed as ſin to the perſon, though it remaine in the nature, the guilt being remitted to the regenerate by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of God.<note place="margin">Gregor. lib: 5. in lib: 1. Reg: cap: 1. Quid eſt, quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorat legem ineſſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bris legi mentis re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pugnantem, ſi extinctis alijs, alij in fugam verſi ſunt: niſi quia perfecti viri hoc ipſum quod ſimplices motus carnis contra voluntatem ſuſtinent, vehementer dolent? vellent quippe ſic ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere in carne, vt contra mentis voluntatem, de carne nulla ſuſtinerent, quod quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quia impoſsibile eſt, praemiſit, dicens: velle adjacet mihi, poſſe non inuenio: non enim quod volo bonum hoc ago, ſed quod odi malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, illud facio, quaſi dicat, vellem eſſe in carne, non ea perfectione, qua perfectus in carne perfectus eſt, ſed ſicut Angeli Dej in Coelo, ſed hoc poſſe non invenio, quia quamdiu mors peccati abſorpta, in futura reſurrectione non fuerit, illud quod in me peccatum inhabitat, mouet me contra me. Fran. White. Obſer. 2. Sect: 2. Auguſtine, vt ſupra.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons why God loueth theſe irregular mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſtil in the Regenerate, we may learne out of the Fathers alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1 For our ſpirituall exerciſe of our Faith, Patience,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7780:11"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Watchfulneſſe, Inuocation, to humble vs, to make vs know our ſelues,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologia David cap. 2 in fine: See Greg. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Lib. 33. ca. 11, &amp; Hieron. aduerſ. Pelag. lib. 2. &amp; Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten. lib. de Cor. &amp; gra. cap. 9. in ſine. Aug. de bapt. Parv. cap. 39. Iudg. 3, 1.</note> &amp; what need we haue of Chriſt: to keepe vs waking, to ſhake off ſecurity and drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to gather our wits and forces together, to ſtand vpon our guard, to depend vpon God, to call vpon him for ayde, to flye and cleaue faſt vnto him; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if his Grace doe not continually ſupporte vs, we are not able to ſtand. Theſe are (ſayth S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>) the Nations left in <hi>Canaan</hi> (which their <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua,</hi> our Ieſus caſt not out) <hi>Quas dereliquit Dominus vt erudiret in eis Ieruſalem:</hi> which God left to teach, and exerciſe his people withall; and which (if they grew careleſſe) ſhould bee as prickes and goades in their ſides, and thornes in theyr eyes, and that they ſhould not thinke they were come yet to theyr finall reſt, but ſhould ſtill looke for a better.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2 Againe, that Gods children may be examples of all holy vertues to others (and thereby glorious to his name) which were nothing if the obiect and matter whereon they worke were aboliſhed: where were <hi>Patience</hi> if there were no afflictions? where <hi>Grace</hi> if no temptations? where <hi>Mortification</hi> if no luſts to mortifie? where <hi>Temperance, Sobriety, Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> if no oppoſition, no motions to ſinne? where were the battell, the victory, the crowne, if no aduerſary to ſtriue withall?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Againe, leſt men ſhould become religious on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be freed from this diſquietneſſe of the ſoule, &amp; diſeaſes of the body, and other griefes and penalties of this life: which were to make them <hi>molliores,</hi> not <hi>meliores,</hi> more tender to themſelues then tendering
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7780:11"/> their duties, to ſeeke to build a Heauen vpon Earth, without deſire of a better. But here God will haue vs ſtill prouoked with theſe, ſtill <hi>militant,</hi> and in the Combat, to fight the Lords battels, as againſt other enemies, ſo againſt our owne luſtes, to ſtriue for the victory, to obtaine the Crowne, to bee wayned from the loue of this world, and long for the perfection &amp; glory of the world to come.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Since then this body of death is not yet dead in the beſt Regenerate. My deare brother, thou that art weake and doubtfull of thy ſtate, faint thou not, bee not too much deiected and diſmaied (as if thou wert out of Gods fauour) becauſe thou feeleſt ſuch moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in thee, and haply thinkeſt that Gods beloued children are free from ſuch temptations. It is not ſo: they bee the <hi>Symptoms</hi> and paſſions of the beſt men, left ſtill in them by the diſpenſation of Gods wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to good purpoſe. That wee ſhould not thinke them of higher nature then our ſelues,<note place="margin">Amb. apol. David. c. 2.</note> but ſubiect to the like paſſions: to which end they are ſometimes ſuffered to fall, and theyr falles recorded, and as ill may wee ſpare the knowledge of theyr falles for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, as the examples of their vertues for imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. S. <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſeth he felt theſe motions, &amp; Gods bleſſed Saints on earth, were neuer free from them. It is obſerued in S. <hi>Hierom</hi> (which he bewrayes in many places of his works) that his whole life was a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all war with his own luſts.</p>
            <p>This is not the difference betwixt the Regenerate and vnregenerate, that the one is free from euil luſts, the other feeles him: but this, The one labours to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7780:12"/> mortifie them,<note place="margin">Epiphanius hereſ. 64. Sicut quando caprificus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git radices in muro, leu aedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio, quantum cunoue ſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur, manet radix, opus eſt murum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruere, &amp; tunc reaedificabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſine radice: ſic in corpore iſto mortali fit, in quo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix manet peccati, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcentia nempe rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, donec mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur, &amp; iteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaedificetur per reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem. This Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by both ſides, by Tolet, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, Tractat. 2. in loca Ep. ad Rom. cap. 7. And by D. Field that learned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. Lib. 3. of the church. c. 26.</note> the other giues the raigne vnto them. If thou doeſt then miſlike them, labour to ſuppreſſe and mortifie them, and ſo ſhew the power of Gods grace working in thee. Thou art a happy man, and in the caſe of Gods bleſſed children: the greater thy temptations are, the more noble is thy reſiſtance, the more exemplary thy life and vertues, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall bee thy Crowne and glory. S. <hi>Paul</hi> cryeth out to the Lord (2. Cor. 12.8, 9.) to be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this pricke of the fleſh, this Meſſenger of Sathan, ſent to buffet him, but the Lord anſwered, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee, for my ſtrength is made perfect in thy weakeneſſe.</hi> Gods grace is ſufficient to enable vs to repreſſe them, though it bee not his pleaſure to free vs from them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 2 Preſume not of thine owne righteouſneſſe, as if it could ſatiſfie Gods iuſtice, &amp; ſtand betwixt thee and thy condemnation. They that doe ſo, (I doubt) are farre from true Regeneration, which makes a man ſee into himſelfe, and finde many thinges to craue pardon for nothing wherein he may greatly glorie. The meere Naturall and ciuill man (who haue yet no true feeling of Religion) may thinke highly of theyr owne righteouſneſſe (as the Phariſe did, Luc, 18.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was no groſſe extortioner) but the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man will finde imperfections enow in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth here, and though hee dayly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that his righteouſneſſe may exceed the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, yet his opinion of it will alwayes come ſhort of<note place="margin">Aug. Lib: 3. de Doctr. Chriſtiana, c. 23. ſpeaking of Davids and other Saintes ſins, teacheth that no man can brag of his iuſtice, or contemno others. Cum videat tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum virorum, &amp; cavendas tempeſtates, &amp; ſlenda naufragia.</note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7780:12"/> theyrs. He will learn to know that the law is ſtraight, and requireth <hi>totum hominem</hi> the whole man, with all the parts and powers of body and ſoule: to keepe <hi>totam lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the whole law, with euery branch and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle thereof, and that <hi>totaliter,</hi> and <hi>toto vitae tempore,</hi> his whole life throughout, without, omitting any minute or moment thereof: for (<hi>Iames.</hi> 2.10.) <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guilty of all.</hi> And as the Law is ſtraite, ſo the Curſe is large. Gal. 3, 10. <hi>Curſed is euery one that continueth not in all things which are written in the Booke of the Law to doe them.</hi> And therefore with S. <hi>Paul</hi> he ſhall finde no perfection in himſelfe to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie him. (<hi>Philip.</hi> 3.12.) but rather ſin to condemne him (as here) and conſequently will be driuen out of himſelfe to ſeeke for ayde, euen to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who is made vnto vs <hi>Wiſdome and righteouſneſſe, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> and <hi>Redemption,</hi> 1. Cor. 1.30. And euer when hee looketh aduiſedly into himſelfe, hee wil be ſo farre from thinking himſelfe iuſt, that he will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crie out of his imperfections with S. <hi>Paul</hi> heere,
<q>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> 3 Truſt not to the <hi>ſuperogatory</hi> merites of Gods Saints, they are ſo vnable to helpe thee, that they were not ſufficient to ſaue themſelues, their workes ſtill needing Gods mercy to forgiue, and ſtill ſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſome imperfections of right and infection of ſinne. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> here diſableth himſelfe, and <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19.23. concludeth all men within ſinne, that God might haue mercy vpon all. It is a fine Dreame
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7780:13"/> of the Papiſts, that the ſuperaboundant merits and ſufferings of holy men, more then needed for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, are to be diſpenſed and diſpoſed of, by the great huſband of the Church the Pope, and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to other men that will giue well for them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon is grounded that <hi>Great trading of Pardons,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by the merites of Saintes are often ſolde (but neuer deliuered) to men that need, and theſe merits are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Treaſures of the Church,</hi> and ſo they are indeed (as our excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t King noteth in his Preface to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes) for they bring great treaſures to the Popes coffers. I can but wonder that waking men will be deluded by ſuch dreames.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> 4 Beare charitable conceites of thoſe that are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken with ſinne, that haue made a good profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet ſometimes are foiled as <hi>Lot, Noah, Dauid, Peter;</hi> as ſometimes a word may eſcape, euen a wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which he wiſheth were vnſpoken: ſo ſomtimes ſin may eſcape a wary man, which he is ſorry for, &amp; ſurely temptations are ſo great, and our natural pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo little, that without Gods grace continually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting vs, we cannot ſtand, but ſhould doubtleſſe often fall into many ſins. Prayſe we God for giuing ſuch meaſure of grace vnto frayle men, and feare wee him for withdrawing it ſometimes, to let them ſee theyr weakeneſſe: pitty them and pray for them, &amp; vſe Saint <hi>Paules</hi> counſell, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. <hi>If any fall by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion into any fault, you that are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch a one with the Spirit of Meekeneſſe, conſidering thy ſelfe, leaſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Laſtly, hunger, thirſt, and long for that time, when
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7780:13"/> all imperfection ſhall ceaſe, and be aboliſhed, when this corruptible ſhall put on incorruption, and this mortall ſhall put on immortality, this Naturall body ſhall become ſpirituall, and this body of death ſhall bee done away, when we ſhall dwell in the Lande of promiſe, without theſe Cananites prickes, &amp; goades in our ſides, and thornes in our eyes, and when wee ſhall not cry out, <hi>O wretched men who ſhall deliuer vs?</hi> but ioyfully ſing, <hi>O happy men that are ſo graciouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from this body of death!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much for the ſecond point, the thirde fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doc. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>The Regenerate doe ſee and feele their ſinnes, more then other men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So it appeares S. <hi>Paul</hi> did, when ſo feelingly and mouingly he ſpake of this Law in his members, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling, and ſo paſſionately cryed out, <hi>O Wretched ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I am!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>I</label> Surely, the Regenerate haue leſſe ſins then other, but they ſee them more. <note place="margin">for ſeeing.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is twofold, Firſt their true iudging what ſinne is. 2. Their due and vnpartiall looking into themſelues; for they are alwayes reading on 2, Bookes, the Booke of Gods Law (teaching what they ſhould doe) and the booke of their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (regiſtring what they doe.) They attend &amp; hearken to the Law of God, and by it frame theyr iudgement of ſinne, not like vaine men, iudging on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that good that agrees to their corrupt and miſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen reaſon: that only evill, that diſlikes theyr fancy, and ſo make themſelues Iudges of the law;<note place="margin">Iam. 4.11.</note> but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7780:14"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> reforming their iudgements, and by the <hi>Dictates</hi> of the Law (which is the perfect rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) they come to the true knowledge of ſinne (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth here, I had not knowne that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence was ſinne, but that the Law ſayth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not luſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.</note>) So they haue <hi>Lumen internum &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum,</hi> Externall of the Word, which is a light and a lantherne, Internal of the Spirit, which enlightneth the eyes of their vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105. Ioh. 16.13.</note> and leades them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Truth: And by this Spirit alſo, their <hi>ſelfe-loue</hi> is diminiſhed and ſwalowed vp in their loue of God, ſo that they looke into themſelues more vnpartially, as a man therefore walking in darkeneſſe, or neuer looking vpon himſelfe, ſees no ſpots, durt, deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vpon him, but thinks all is well: but comming to the light, and viewing himſelfe well, hee ſees many things vnthought of before, and is much abaſhed: ſo it is with the Naturall man, he perceyueth nothing, but thinks all is well, (for he walks in darkeneſſe) and wanteth light or liſt to looke into himſelfe, but the Regenerate man ſpyes all, and whatſoeuer he findes, comparing it with the Rule, he iudgeth rightly of it. The Spirituall man diſcerneth all things.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Againe, as he hath light beyond that of Nature to ſee, <note place="margin">for Feeling.</note> ſo hee hath life and quickneſſe of the Spirite to feele, the ſkinne of his conſcience is tender, and eaſily offended, which in others is hard and brawny, and hath loſt his feeling. And therefore whereas others, at horrible, abominable, and odious ſins are nothing moved (as being dead in ſin,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.2.</note> their conſciences feared and paſt feeling:) S. <hi>Paul</hi> at the ſmalleſt ſins that can
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7780:14"/> be felt, euen at the firſt motions of ſinne, which ſtirre within him, is offended and grieued, and cryeth out as at deadly wounds of his ſoule: <hi>O wretched man that I am, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Here is a Comfort for Gods children. That wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome count it a heauy caſe for a man to ſee and feele his ſinnes, &amp; to haue grieuous pangs for them, and thinke it neere vnto deſpayre and reprobation: Let them know, that to be ſenſible of a mans ſins, is a ſigne of Grace &amp; Regeneration, and of a tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that he hath light to ſee, and life to feele, that which by Nature he could neyther ſee nor feele, ſuch a heart is now prepared for comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> And here is a corſiue for wicked men, paſt feeling: their ſtate is wofull, for it argueth that they haue not attended to the law of God, to come by the true knowledge of ſinne: or haue not vſed to turn their eyes to looke into themſelues. Happily they haue oft looked on other mens Dyals, but neuer marked how the clocke ſtrikes in their owne boſome, wildly paſſing on and thinking all well, or groſly iudging of ſinne by their owne corrupt reaſon: and ſo blind to ſee, and ſenceleſſe to feele theyr owne euils, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know not what neede they haue of Chriſt, and conſequently neuer ſeeke after him. This ſenceleſneſſe is a ſigne of no regeneration, no-inhabiting of Gods Spirit, no life or light of grace, which is the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of glory and happineſſe. That wound (ſayth S. <hi>Auſten</hi>) is not beſt to be liked, that feeles leaſt paine, (for that may proceed of dead fleſh within it) but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which is quick of ſence, and feeleth the leaſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7780:15"/> touch: ſo for the ſoule, for corruption is not felt by corruption, but by grace, and the more grace a man hath, the tenderer is his conſcience, and the more he feeles his owne corruption. But (to proceed) where this true feeling of ſin is, there will follow true gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for it, which is my fourth point. The doctrine is.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doc. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Sinne is the onely thing that grieues the Regenerate.</hi> We neuer find in the hiſtory of the Acts, nor in all Saint <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtles, that euer any thing drawes him into ſuch a pang, as ſinne doth here, to cry out, <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me?</hi> All the euils in the world are ſorted into two rankes, <hi>Malum culpae,</hi> and <hi>Malum paenae:</hi> ſinne and paine: as <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> cals them, <hi>Malum delicti,</hi> and <hi>Malum ſupplicii,</hi> as <hi>Auſten, Peccatum</hi> &amp; <hi>paena peccati: Malum quod facit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, &amp; malum quod patitur homo:</hi> Now the euill that man committeth againſt God, grieues the childe of God much more, then the evil or puniſhment which God inflicts vpon man.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> And the reaſon is good, for ſin is the cauſe of all boyle of paine, but not <hi>contra,</hi> evill of paine is not alwayes cauſe of ſin: Surely, wee had neuer knowne nor felt this euill of paine, if ſinne had not brought it into the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Againe, Paine, though euill in our feeling, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our will, yet is good in Gods decreeing, and neuer againſt his will.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Againe, of paine, in aſmuch as it is paine, and a chaſtiſement or puniſhment of ſinne; God is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor: but of ſinne, in as much as it is ſinne, God is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7780:15"/> not the author. Sinne is exceeding offenſiue to him, affliction is not: being but eyther a puniſhment for ſinne committed, by his iuſtice, or a good meanes to preuent it, by his mercy; ſo ſinne is our ſickneſſe, paine is our phyſicke, and though the phyſicke bee bitter, (as much wholeſome phyſicke is) yet euery wiſe man will endure it rather then the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>Zanchius</hi> his reaſons, to which I adde,<note place="margin">Hieron. Zanc. Tom, 4. Lib 1. De Malo. cap. 2. Theſi. 9.</note> that though there were no paine nor puniſhment for ſin, yet would Gods children hate and abhorre it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it offendeth their good Father, whome they heartily loue, and would euer pleaſe: and becauſe it ſpotteth and defileth their ſoules with filthineſſe, which they would keepe clean as the Temples of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> concludes with mee: The wicked men hate paine more then ſinne, but the godly hate ſinne more then paine.<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 3. de Civitate Dei cap. 1. Mala paenae magis odio haberi a malis, quam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mala culpae: contra mala culpae magis odiſſe bonos, quam mala paenae. Saint Paules righteouſnes.</note> A true difference betwixt godly and profaine men; the vngodly will aduenture vpon any ſinne to enioy pleaſure, &amp; auoid paine: the godly will aduenture vpon any pain, euen death it ſelfe to auoyde ſinne, as wee ſee in many bleſſed Martyrs, and all godly men, that will take vp their Croſſe to follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Surely Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ſinne was little, and his paine much, yet he neuer complaines of his afflictions, but eryes out moſt bitterly of his ſin, <hi>O wretched man that I am who ſhall deliuer me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.6. He ſayth touching the righteouſneſſe of the Law, he liued vnrebukeably, even before hee was conuerted, mans eye could ſpie no fault in him, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7780:16"/> 1. Cor. 4.4. he ſayth, he knew nothing by himſelfe: And Act. 24.14. avoweth to the face of his moſt quicke ſighted aduerſaries, that hee truely worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the God of his Fathers, beleeuing all things in the law and the Prophets, had hope in the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead, and laboured to haue a cleare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards God &amp; man. Act. 20. he proteſteth to the Elders of Epheſus, whom hee had ſent for to Miletum, and taketh them to witneſſe after what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he had liued with them at all ſeaſons, ſeruing the Lord with all humility, and with many teares and tentations, and how he paſſed not for bonds and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, neyther was his life deare vnto him, ſo that he might fulfill his courſe with ioy, and the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which hee had receiued of the Lord Ieſus, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Goſpell of the grace of God.</p>
            <p>2. Tim. 4.6. When hee was now ready to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the time of his departing was at hand, his conſcience could giue him this teſtimony, I haue fought a good fight, and haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith: From henceforth is layde vp for me the crowne of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord that righteous Iudge ſhall giue mee at that day, and not to me onely, but vnto them alſo that loue his appearing: ſuch was his righteouſneſſe: and will you view his afflictions?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Saint Paules afflictions.</note>To omit all thoſe ſlaunders, raylings, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſcourges in other Chapters before, of the Acts of the Apoſtles: we haue eight whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at the end, of nothing but his troubles and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, how he was violently taken by his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7780:16"/> out of the holy Temple, what an vprore was there about him, that he hardly eſcaped tearing in peeces of them: how more then forty of the Iewes ſware his death, and lay in wayte for him: how hec was poſted from one priſon to another, from one ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to another, kept in bands and ward like an euill doer: and when the magiſtrate had openly pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him guiltleſſe, yet could he haue no right, but was ſtill kept in bands, eyther for fauour of the Iews, or in hope to wring ſome money out of him for his deliuerance: and therefore hee was examined, and reexamined, and for all his Innocency, muſt eyther bee deliuered into the hands of his bloody enemies, vnder pretence to be iudged at Ieruſalem, but indeed to be murdred by the way, or elſe muſt appeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the higheſt monarch of the world to defend him, and ſo preferre a troubleſome and a dangerous iourney before a trayterous and a murderous death. And this iourney to Rome is deſcribed through the dangerous ſeas, amongſt the Iſlands, in the depth of winter, where the winds, tempeſts, ſeas, and ſouldiers ſtroue which ſhould be the cruelleſt: ſo that when the ſhip brake by the fury of the winds and tempeſts, the ſouldiers would haue killed the priſoners, leaſt they might ſcape by ſwimming, more barbarous then the<note n="a" place="margin">So the Italian cals the ſea.</note> barbarous Element. Which of vs ſhould not haue cried out in ſuch extremity of our great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, rather then at our ſinnes: <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet all theſe troubles are eaſie to that great throng of evils, which hee reckoneth vp of himſelfe, 2. Cor.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7780:17"/> 11.23. In Labours aboundant, in ſtripes aboue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in priſons frequent, in death often: 24. of the Iewes 5. times receyued I40. ſtripes ſaue one. 25. Thrice was I beaten with rods, Once was I ſtoned, thrice I ſuffered ſhipwracke, a night and a day haue I bin in the deepe, 26. In iourneying often, in perils of waters, in perils of Robbers, in perils by my owne Countrymen, in perils by the heathen, in perils in the City, in perils in the wilderneſſe, in perils in the Sea, in perils amongſt falſe brethren: 27. In wearineſſe and painefulneſſe, in watchings often, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, 28. beſide thoſe things that are without, that which commeth vpon me dayly, the care of all Churches. 29 Who is offended and I burne not: 31. The God and Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which is bleſſed for euermore, knoweth that I lie not.</p>
            <p>What naturall man in the world, would not theſe troubles deepely amaze, and driue into a deſperate ſence, and ſet him at his wits end, to cry out of his wretchedneſſe and miſerable miſhappes, that fall ſo thicke vpon him, eſpecially falling ſo vndeſeruingly, as they did vpon Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> But what ſayth S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe vnto them? Behold the patterne of a true Regenerate man. I count (ſayth he) that the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent time are not worthy of the glory, which ſhall bee ſhewed vnto vs, Rom. 8.18. and 2. Cor. 4, 17. Our light affliction which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent, and an eternall waight of glory, and therefore he ſayth, 2. Cor. 12.10. I take pleaſure in infirmities, in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7780:17"/> in neceſſities, in perſecutions for Chriſts ſake. And Act. 21, 13. He proteſteth that hee is not onely ready to be bound, but alſo to die for the name of the Lord Ieſus. His troubles though great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſeeme nothing in his eyes, but when hee lookes vpon the leaſt ſinne that is poſſible to be in man, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the leaſt motion of the fleſh that ſtirreth againſt the Spirit, it doth ſo grieue him, and ſeeme ſo odious in his eyes, that hee cryeth out in the agony of his ſoule. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Excellent and diuine Apoſtle, <note place="margin">A compariſon of our State with S. Paules, In malis eulpae &amp; in malis paenae.</note> how farre doeſt thou out-goe vs, on the one ſide in all holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, and on the other ſide in croſſes and afflictions, and yet paſſing ouer thy afflictions with ioy that are ſo great &amp; many, onely cryeſt out of thy ſins that are ſo few and ſmall: and we at euery light affliction are ready to murmur and rage with impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, but for our ſins (whoſe magnitude and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude cannot bee eſteemed) we grieue not at all, but remayne inſenſible. O well were we (thinke the moſt men) if wee could liue in wealth and eaſe, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this world, without any croſſe or affliction, to diſquiet our minds, or hinder our delights, how well could we fat our ſelues with pleaſure, and neuer think of our ſinnes, to moue vs to ſorrow and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly! But alaſſe (deere brethren) we ſhould make this vſe of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> example (to omit other) to ſearch our owne harts and courſes, and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſins, and of our wretchedneſſe by them,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7780:18"/> and be hartily ſorry for offending our God, defiling our ſelues,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.13. The ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the world.</note> and drawing heauy plagues and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vppon vs, knowing, that if the Righteous ſcarcely bee ſaued, where ſhall the wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly appeare. Alaſſe, who can looke into the World, but he ſhall finde in all Eſtates, and in all degrees, in all theyr courſes, that there is no whole party, no found part, but from head to foot, all ouerrunne with this ſoule Leproſie of ſinne.<note place="margin">Tit. 4. laſt.</note> They profeſſe that they know GOD, but by Workes they deny him, are become abhominable and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, and to euery good Worke reprobate: Iuſt like the Cretians,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.12.</note> lyars to the Trueth, Euill beaſtes, ſlow bellyes, ſlowe to doe good, but to any euill quicke and forward.</p>
            <p>Who can goe into the ſtreetes but hee ſhall heare ſtore of wicked blaſphemous oathes, vngodly ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, filthy, talking, rotten ſpeeches in euery corner: theyr mouthes are as open Sepulchres, breathing out corrupt and filthy ſtinkes from the rotten carrion of their hearts, as if the ſound of the Goſpell had neuer rung in their, eares, neuer ſuncke into their hearts to ſeaſon them.</p>
            <p>What iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> would not continually vexe his righteous Soule by dwelling amongſt them, and ſeeing their wicked conuerſation?<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2, 7.8.</note> What good <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> eyes would not guſh out with tears to ſee Gods lawes ſo contemned,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.53.158. Ierem. 9.1. &amp; Lament.</note> what good <hi>Ieremie</hi> would not melt away in Lamentations to ſee the wickedneſſe, and to foreſee the miſeries of his people, yea
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7780:18"/> What good Chriſtian can temper himſelfe from crying out in theyr behalfe: <hi>O Wretched men that wee are, who ſhall deliuer vs from this body of death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alaſſe wretched men whether ſhall wee turne vs?<note place="margin">Little mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> whoſe liues are nothing but a continuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of ſinne? who very weakely and coldly reſiſt theſe motions of ſinne that ſtirre in our natures, but ſuffer them to get the vpper hand ouer vs.</p>
            <p>What ſhall become of them that reſiſt not at all,<note place="margin">Or none at all, but rather foſtering of ſin full motions. Iob. 20.12.</note> but gladly and willingly entertaine them, and like a man that hath gotten a ſweet morſell in his mouth, turneth it with his tongue, and delights in the chew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſayth) that take pleaſure and delight to thinke and muſe, and feed their corrupt fancies with ruminating and ſtudying of their ſin, and wiſh time and oportunity to execute them, and put them in practiſe, ſo farre from reſiſting and mortifying, that they are ſorry for nothing ſo much, as that they haue not ſtrength enough by nature, or liberty, enough by law to glut their deſires with the ful fruition of them; the drunkard in his ſwiniſhneſſe, the Lecher in his gotiſhneſſe, the couetous in his rauenouſneſſe, the malicious in his poyſonouſneſſe, and others in theyr ſeuerall wickedneſſe, that labour not to bridle their luſtes, but more to kindle and enflame them, to the vttermoſt of theyr power, and if theyr owne weakeneſſe did not reſtraine them, or the feare of humane Laws and puniſhments curbe them, they would be yet more outragiouſly wicked, and damnably ſinfull. Alaſſe, wretched men, who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7780:19"/> ſhall deliuer them from the body of this death? whom could it not iuſtly aſtoniſh in this light of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Sinning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumaciouſly, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th a hie band.</note> to ſee ſuch a ſtupid careleſneſſe of ſinne, poſſeſſing all men, ſuch a deadneſſe and vnmoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe to any goodneſſe, notwithſtanding, all that euer can bee ſayd or done? Nay, to behold a verie carefulneſſe, a deſire, and a forwardneſſe to offend God, and oppoſe our ſelues againſt his precepts, that men account it their onely glory and valour to liue irregularly, with contempt of all good faſhions, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, gouernment, yea, with contempt of God and Man? as (for example) when the Lord pronounceth a woe to them that are mighty to drinke Wine, and ſtrong to poure in ſtrong drinke (Eſay 5.22.) ſome (that are not aſhamed ſtill to call themſelues Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) count it a gallant matter and a great glory to drinke downe one another, and be able to carry it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as if they would purpoſely oppoſe themſelues againſt God and his laws, and ſtand at defiance with him, and not content with old ſins, known to former ages, will needs be the inventers of new ſinnes, new arts of drinking, whoring, cheating, and other villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, their wits, tongues, health, wealth and ſtrength giuen them for Gods ſeruice, they turne all to ſerue ſin ſtrongly, fight againſt God with his owne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and horribly ruſh againſt his commandements and curſes, with ſport and paſtime.</p>
            <p>So when Chriſt ſayth, Sweare not at all, for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is more then yea and nay, proceedeth of euil: they holde it a point of valour and ſtoutneſſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.34.</note> to rap
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7780:19"/> out oathes couragiouſly, and fill vp theyr vnperfect ſpeeches with damnable ſwearing.<note place="margin">Coloſ. 4.6.</note> When the Lorde commaundeth that all our talke be ſauoury and tend to edification: they delight in vnſauoury, idle,<note place="margin">8. Cor. 15.33.</note> filthy talke, and ſuch words as are fitteſt to corrupt good manners, and make themſelues ſport with ſin: And yet (wretched men) what profit is there in theſe ſins? what great pleaſure, what benefite to draw them?</p>
            <p>The Prophet ſpeaketh in the Lords name, as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring that men will ruſh into ſinne, and endaunger their ſoules for ſmall matters, for a handfull of barley and a peece of bread, (Ezech. 13.19.) but our people ſweare, blaſpheme, vſe all beaſtly talke and filthy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, for no profite at all, for no credite, but only for a cuſtome in ſinning, a deueliſh deſire to doe that they are forbidden, or in the folly of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites, and the curriſh rage of their pride, or to ſhew courage that they care neyther for God nor man.</p>
            <p>But in thoſe ſinnes that are ioyned with profite (if you looke vpon worldlings) what villany doe they ſticke at? to rake to themſelues, to oppreſſe the poor,<note place="margin">Specially where Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon raigneth.</note> to betray the innocent, to defraude theyr next kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to coſen their deareſt &amp; neereſt friends, to racke poore Tenants, to teare it out of their maws, to grind their faces, nay worſe, to turne them out of doores, to pull down towns and houſes, and like Canibals to deuoure one another? The greater ſort, as tyrants preying vpon the inferiors, without pitty or loue at all, but treading vpon them to ſtand the higher, the inferiour as ſlaues againe without any loue or reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the higher, but grudging at them, as at an
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7780:20"/> vnſupportable lode, which if they had ſtrength, they would ſhake off.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The height &amp; commonneſſe of Sinne.</note>Generally, what is the skill and cunning of a man, but to entrappe one another, without being intrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, their wiſedome but a fine cleane conueyance of villany, their profeſſion but a cloake of hypocriſie: all theyr outward vertue, but a falſe colour to hide theyr inward vices? and how are the fineſt wits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, but in ſmoothing ouer foule actions with fayre gloſſes, and varniſhing ouer their crackes and flawes, that they bee not ſpyed: and in contriuing wicked practiſes cunningly, to bring them to paſſe effectually, with theyr beſt aduantage, and leaſt cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the world, or penalty of Lawes, all without any regard of God &amp; his commandements, or any ſenſe of Religion, as if thou (O God) waſt not the Iudge of the world, but ſom dead Idol, which had no care of what we do here below, or heard not, or ſaw not thoſe things that ate done in the world. Alaſſe, <hi>Wretched men that we are, who ſhall deliuer vs from this body of death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reuerend men and Brethren, I would be ſory that theſe wordes ſhould bee without all exception vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of all (God forbid) I ſpeake of many,<note place="margin">A revocation and preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the laſt Doctrine.</note> not of all: of the general courſe of the world, out of which God hath reſerued ſome that abhorre ſuch wickedneſſe: yea (bleſſed be his name) there are ſome (and that a good ſome) euen in this place, that ſhine as lightes in the midſt of this crooked and wicked generation,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.15. Acts 24.16.</note> that labour with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to keepe a cleare conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7780:20"/> towards God and men, to be a holy Nation,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9. Tit. 2.14.</note> a royall Prieſthood, a peculiar people, zealous of good works, and ſhew forth the vertues of him, that hath called them out of darkeneſſe into his maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light. Bleſſed bee God for them, and God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the number of them: but the greater ſort are carryed away with the ſtreame of the world, and go the broad way of deſtruction, and euen the beſt, while they are in this fleſh, are not without imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and this mouing of the body of ſinne within them (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was,) and had neede to crye out as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did: <hi>O wretched men that wee are, who ſhall deliuer vs from this body of Death?</hi> As for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that drinke downe ſinne like water, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye nothing to their hearts luſts that they ſtand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; what hope can they haue to be deliuered? moſt wretched men that we are, who ſhall deliuer vs from this bodie of death, and the plagues thereto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging? Yes, there is a meane yet to be deliuered, if they would ſeeke it, if they would conſider Gods lawes, and ſearch their own conſciences, and ſo come to the feeling, the acknowledging, and ſorrowing for their ſins, and thinke themſelues wretched for them, (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> did here) then ſhould they goe forwards with him, to that which I propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ſpeake of in the laſt place: To ſeeke and finde a Remedie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them: For he that ſeeketh findeth, he that as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth receyueth, and he that knocketh at the doore of Gods mercy, ſhal haue it opened: the laſt doctrine is</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>The true feeling of our ſinnes, will make vs earneſtly ſeeke for a remedie.</hi> As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did heere, finding
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7780:21"/> himſelfe wretched by ſin, cryeth, <hi>Who ſhall deliuer me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> For, it is naturall for all men diſquieted, diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and grieued, to ſeeke for eaſe: yea, for all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the ſillyeſt worme in the world doth naturally ſeeke all contentment, decline and auoyde all things hurtfull, and ſeeke remedyes for griefes, and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer the creature is, the more it doth it. And therfore as the ſight and feeling of our wounds, makes vs ſeek to the Chyrurgion, our ſicknes to the Phyſitian, our wrongs to the Magiſtrate and Lawyer, ſo our ſins for remedie from aboue. But as ſinne is of all euils the greateſt, &amp; the Regenerate of all other the moſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereof: ſo they ſeeke for the remedy of this euill, aboue all others, yea, ſinne in all men doth ſo much offend the Conſcience, when it is awaked, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all naturall griefe, it growes reſtles, and beyond all meaſure vnſupportable, trying all poſſible means of eaſe, which if it finde not, it growes deſperate, and ventureth vpon any violent death, to be his own exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner, to make an ende of the preſent torment, for it is more vntollerable then death it ſelfe, (as wee ſee in <hi>Iudas,</hi> who when his eyes were opened to ſee his ſinne, went to the high Prieſts, confeſſed his ſinne, and his wrong vnto the Innocent, caſt downe the Money, but finding no comfort, went and hanged himſelfe.)</p>
            <p>But to his Children, God ſendeth a comfort in due ſeaſon, when it is truely and faithfully ſought: which is to them the welcomeſt and gladſommeſt thing in the world. Therefore the Law was profitably giuen, <hi>vt ſit Pedagogus ad Chriſtum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.24.</note> to be our Schoolmaſter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7780:21"/> vnto <hi>CHRIST, non vt ſanet, ſed vt aegrotum te eſſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat:</hi> not to heale thee, but to ſhew thee thy ſicknes, and make thee ſeeke to the Phyſition; for that makes vs finde, what neede we haue of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>A man neuer knowes the worth of Chriſt, till hee ſee his owne vnworthineſſe and danger, neuer ſeekes for eaſe and comfort, till hee feele the loade and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of his ſinnes, and is grieued at the loathſomnes of his corruptions, and foreſees the miſery they bring vpon him. But when his eyes are once opened to ſee this, doubtleſſe hee will ſeeke to be deliuered, and the wiſer hee is, the ſooner.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> And therefore (me thinks) I may make this vſe of this Doctrine, <note place="margin">To ſtirre vp men to ſeeke remedie for their ſinne.</note> that hee that ſeekes not for deliuerie from this body of death, eyther he feeles it not, or is exceedingly beſotted in loue with his owne ſicknes: eyther he is blinde, and ſees not his eſtate: or ſeeing it, is madde, that ſeekes not to relieue it, Chooſe (all you impenitent ſinners) in whether of theſe ranks you wil be placed, amongſt blinde men, or mad men, that will not ſee, or ſeeing will not ſeeke Deliuerance from this bodie of death.</p>
            <p>For it is not poſſible that a man fallen into a pit, ſhould not deſire to be helped out: that a man dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ſicke ſhould not deſire to recouer: that a man grieuouſly wounded ſhould not deſire to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: that a man in Priſon and durance ſhould not deſire libertie: at leaſt if hee feele his euill, and the danger of it, eyther blindneſſe or madneſſe poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, But indeede no man can be ſo madde, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be firſt blinde: blinded with the cuſtome of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7780:22"/> ſinne, that makes vs vnſenſible: or with the prince of darkeneſſe that luls men a ſleepe with the pleaſures of ſinne,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4 4.</note> to forget their eſtate, or blinded with ſome Phariſaicall opinion of their owne righteouſnes, like the Laodiceans that ſayd they were rich, and had need of nothing, and knew not they were wretched and miſerable,<note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> and poore and blind, and naked, for if they had the true eye-ſalue, and that their eies were opened to ſee their wofull eſtate by ſinne: this ſhould be the firſt thing they would goe about, the greateſt buſineſſe they would intend to ſeeke ſome deliuery, and to com to ſome comfortable aſſurance of Gods fauour.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 10.42. Matth: 13.46. Phil. 3.8.</note>This ſhould be the <hi>vnum neceſſarium:</hi> the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pearle that the Marchant would ſell all that euer he had to purchaſe: and they would with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> count all other things (all honour, wealth, pleaſure, &amp; worldly contentments) but loſſe and dung in reſpect of it. <note place="margin">Highly to eſteeme of this Remedie.</note> So ſweete and ioyfull would it bee vnto theyr ſoules.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to inſinuate ſo much, by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry marſhalling of his wordes and phraſes, in deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this doctrine.</p>
            <p>When he looked vpon his ſinnes (though they were as ſmall as poſſibly could bee in any man) they ſeemed ſo foule in his eyes, ſo grieuous to his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo contrary to his cleane deſires, that he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe wretched for them, and paſſionately ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for deliuerance, but finding no meanes in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but a plaine impoſſibility, by reaſon of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored imperfections, hee goeth out of himſelfe, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7780:22"/> asketh, <hi>Who ſhall deliuer me?</hi> and vpon asking the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, preſently giues the ſolution, not in plaine termes (for the fulneſſe of his heart, and the greatnes of his ioy would not let him) but in a dutifull prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of thankefulneſſe, <hi>I thanke God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, It is the mercy of God, that hath ſent his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt to redeem vs, by whome wee are deliuered from this body of death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by him wee are iuſtified from our ſinnes, and ſanctified by his Grace to repreſſe ſinne: and though ſinne ſtill dwell in vs, Yet there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1</note> that walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit, that haue not the fleſh, but the Spirite for their guid, and though they walke weakely and faintingly after it, yet ſtill they follow it as their deſired guid, as wel as the weakeneſſe of their nature will ſuffer.</p>
            <p>This ſeemed ſo worthy a benefite in Saint <hi>Paules</hi> eyes, vpon the thought of his ſinnefull, vncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate on the one ſide, and that moſt gladdſome deliuerie on the other ſide, that hee cannot without an eiaculation of thankefulneſſe expreſſe it, <hi>I thanke God through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Which wordes I cannot ſtand vpon, onely I note, Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Phraze teacheth vs, that this worthy benefite of our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of our Redemption, and Saluation, is neuer to be ſpoken of without thankſgiuing, neuer to be thought of without a gratefull lifting vp of our hearts vnto God, neuer to be named without great admiration and reuerence.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Concluſion, with a recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation of the firſt Doctrine, and vſes.</label> And therefore wee thanke thee O Lord for this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7780:23"/> amongſt all other benefites: for this aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther benefites:and we beſeech thee to giue vs grace to looke into our ſelues, light to ſee our ſinnes, and life to feele them, that we may be humbled by them, and ſeeke to mortifie them, <note place="margin">The ſecond.</note> that we may know, ſee &amp; feele what vnperfect ſtate we liue in here in this fleſh wherein thy deareſt children feele theſe prickes in the fleſh,theſe Cananites and Iebuſites, as prickes and goades in theyr ſides, and thornes in theyr eyes, theſe meſſengers of Sathan to buffet them: that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">With the Vſes.</note> we may bee out of conceyte with our own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,and all humane merites, as not able to ſatiſfie thy iuſtice, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> cleaue the more ſtedfaſtly to thy mercy, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> to the merites of thy ſonne our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: and yet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> be not cleane deiected, as men vtterly ſecluded from thy fauour, by means of our vnperfect ſanctification (ſince ſuch thou wilt haue the ſtate of thy children here vpon earth) but that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> wee may la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ouercome all temptations, and be examples of all holy vertues to others, &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> walke before thee in feare and trembling, euermore hungring and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after that heauenly life, wherein all thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections ſhall be done away.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The third."/> Lord make vs ſenſible of all our wants &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that there be no ſinne in vs, which wee doe not ſee and feele by thy light and grace, and labour to mortifie it, and to hate it as the greateſt euil in the world, that it may bee as vnpleaſant vnto vs as it is vnto thee, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The fourth."/> and that we may heartily ſeeke a remedy, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="The fift."/> with all thankefulneſſe embrace it, and growe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7780:23"/> dayly in grace and all holy vertues, till we become perfect men in Ieſus Chriſt, to the glory of thy great name, the aſſurante of our adoption, the ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our profeſſion, the good and comfort of others, and the eternall comfort of our owne ſoules.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
